Joon Sik Kim

Last Updated: June 23, 2023

I recently graduated from CMU with a PhD in machine learning. My research focuses on methods that can assist our understanding of complex machine learning models, and their application to useful downstream tasks involving human users. Methods include efficient decomposition of neural network predictions, algorithmic fairness assessments; applications include dataset debugging, spurious correlation detection, and assisting human users in document matching. Primarily focused on deep learning models applied to text and image data, the approaches studied include model-agnostic perspectives that can be extended to different data modalities.

CONTACT

Email: davidkim21c0gmail.com
Website: https://wnstlr.github.io

EDUCATION

Carnegie Mellon UniversityPittsburgh, PADoctor of Philosophy, Machine LearningMay 2023Thesis: Methods and Applications of Explainable Machine LearningMay 2023

Advisor: Ameet Talwalkar

Carnegie Mellon University

Master of Science, Machine Learning (GPA 3.86/4.00)

Pittsburgh, PA

May 2020

California Institute of Technology
Bachelor of Science, Computer Science (GPA 4.0/4.3)
Pasadena, CA
June 2017

EXPERIENCE

Microsoft ResearchRedmond, WASummer Research InternJune 2021 - Aug 2021

J.P.Morgan
Summer Intern at AI Research
May 2019 - Aug 2019

SK Inc.

Machine Learning Research Intern

Seoul, South Korea
June 2017 - Aug 2017

Computer Vision Lab, California Institute of Technology

Undergraduate Research Student for Prof. Pietro Perona

Pasadena, CA

July 2016 - Dec 2016

California Institute of Technology

Pasadena, CA

Undergraduate Research Student for Prof. Yisong Yue

June 2015 - June 2016

California Institute of Technology

Pasadena, CA

Undergraduate Research Student for Dr. Vasumathi Raman

July 2014 - Nov 2014

Criminal Investigation Command, Ministry of National Defense

Seoul, South Korea

Soldier, Software Developer, Interpreter

Oct 2012 – July 2014

Laser Interferometer Gravitational-wave Observatory (LIGO)

Pasadena, CA

Undergraduate Research Student for Dr. Parameswaran Ajith

Jan 2012 - Aug 2012

PUBLICATIONS¹

- 9. **Joon Sik Kim**, Valerie Chen, Danish Pruthi, Nihar Shah, Ameet Talwalkar. *Assisting Human Decisions in Document Matching*. Transactions on Machine Learning Research (TMLR), 2023.
- 8. Keegan Harris, Valerie Chen, **Joon Sik Kim**, Ameet Talwalkar, Hoda Heidari, Steven Wu. *Bayesian Persuasion for Algorithmic Recourse*. Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS), 2022.
- 7. **Joon Sik Kim**, Gregory Plumb, Ameet Talwalkar. Sanity Simulations for Saliency Methods. International Conference on Machine Leaning (ICML), 2022. (Spotlight)
- 6. Valerie Chen*, Jeffrey Li*, **Joon Sik Kim****, Gregory Plumb**, Ameet Talwalkar. *Interpretable Machine Learning: Moving From Mythos to Diagnostics*. ACM Queue 19.6 (2022): 28-56.
- Kwangho Kim, Jisu Kim, Manzil Zaheer, Joon Sik Kim, Frederic Chazal, Larry Wasserman. PLLay: Efficient Topological Layer based on Persistence Landscapes. Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS), 2020.
- 4. **Joon Sik Kim**, Jiahao Chen, Ameet Talwalkar. *FACT: A Diagnostic for Group Fairness Trade-offs*. International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), 2020.
- 3. David I. Inouye, Leqi Liu, **Joon Sik Kim**, Bryon Aragam, Pradeep Ravikumar. *Automated Dependence Plots*. Uncertainty in Artificiail Intelligence (UAI), 2020.
- 2. Chih-Kuan Yeh*, **Joon Sik Kim***, Ian E.H. Yen, Pradeep Ravikumar. Representer Point Selection for Explaining Deep Neural Networks. Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS), 2018.
- 1. Matteo Ruggero Ronchi, **Joon Sik Kim**, Yisong Yue. A Rotation Invariant Latent Factor Model for Moveme Discovery from Static Poses. IEEE International Conference on Data Mining (ICDM), 2016.

PRE-PRINTS

1. Valerie Chen, Muyu Yang, Wenbo Cui, **Joon Sik Kim**, Ameet Talwalkar, Jian Ma. Best Practices for Interpretable Machine Learning in Computational Biology. bioRxiv 2022.10.28.513978

PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

Reviewer (FAccT 2023, ICML 2022, FAccT 2022, ICML 2021); Program Committee (Workshop on Fair AI in Finance, NeurIPS 2020).

FELLOWSHIPS, AWARDS

Kwanjeong Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship	2017 - 2021
Caltech Bhansali Family Prize in Computer Science	2017
Caltech CMS Celebration of Undergraduate Research Best Demo/Poster Award	2015
Caltech Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship	2014, 2015, 2016
Caltech Physics 11 Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship	2012

TEACHING

10-725 Convex Optimization (Carnegie Mellon University)	Spring 2023
10-737 Creative AI (Carnegie Mellon University)	Fall 2019

^{1*} indicates equal contribution; includes conference workshop papers